Carlos A. Toruño P.

Development Economist (MSc.)

Contact

♀ Göttingen, Germany

carlos-toruno.com

carlos.toruno@gmail.com

in carlostoruno

ctoruno

Education

Oct. 2019 - Oct. 2021

Development (M.Sc.)

Economics

University of Göttingen Göttingen, Germany

Master's thesis: Political favoritism and social protection policies: Evidence from a cash transfer program in Colombia.

Feb, 2010 - Apr, 2014

Applied Economics (B.Sc.)

Central American University (UCA) Managua, Nicaragua

Bachelor's internship at the Nicaraguan Market Competition Authority.

Feb, 2005 - Dec, 2009

High School Diploma

La Salle High School Managua, Nicaragua

About me

I'm a young economist from Nicaragua with experience as a researcher in development topics. I describe myself as a very organized and pro-active person with high performance in team working, but also as a curious individual with a high level of critical thinking. These characteristics have allowed me to integrate, quickly and easily, into a new professional environment without forgetting that we are in a continuous learning process. My main topics of interest are policy design and evaluation, poverty, inequality, democracy, rule of law and governance.

Work experience

Data Analyst

Apr, 2022 -

World Justice Project (WJP) Washington, D.C.

As part of my daily tasks in the Data Analytics Unit, I process data from the General Population Polls that WJP collects in more than 120 countries worldwide. I also produce data visualizations used in the country reports for these countries; I program dynamic HTML reports and dashboards, and I coordinate the web scraping efforts of WJP to get information for the different projects, among other data-related tasks.

Consultant for political and institutional topics

Nov, 2021 - Mar, 2022

Programa Estado de la Nación (PEN) San José, Costa Rica

I was contracted as a part of a short-term consultancy to support the research agenda on political and institutional topics for Nicaragua. I was in charge of the design and analysis related to the Nicaraguan Post-Electoral Survey 2021, and I supported the elaboration of other specific studies, including a diagnosis of the socioeconomic context of the Nicaraguan youth and the 2022 edition of the state of democracy in Nicaragua.

Senior Economist

Jul, 2018 - Jul, 2019

Nicaraguan Foundation for Social and Economic Development (FUNIDES) *Managua, Nicaragua*

I was responsible for the institutional department. This position involved searching for research opportunities, designing study protocols, coordinating with other researchers, and preparing discussion meetings with development aid agencies and other NGO officers. Some of the research topics the institutional department covers are democracy, governance, the rule of law, politics, and civic and political culture.

Research Assistant

June, 2016 - Jul, 2018

Nicaraguan Foundation for Social and Economic Development (FUNIDES) *Managua, Nicaragua*

As a research assistant, my main responsibilities were to help with the research agenda on social topics like education, health, poverty and inequality. Some of the frequent tasks involved in this position were to clean and analyze administrative data as well as household surveys, prepare tables and plots for technical reports, assist in the design and programming of surveys, perform balance tests and other checks on survey samples, carry focal groups with experts and targeted individuals, and assist in the meetings with governmental and development aid agencies' officers.

Data manipulation and visualization

7 years

Regression analysis

7 years

Survey design and programming

4 years

Quasi-experimental designs

3 years

Program evaluation and experimental designs

2 years

Geospatial analysis

2 years

Web scrapping and Shiny Apps 2 years

Natural Language Processing

1 year

Technologies

R

Stata

LaTex + Markdown

CSPro + ODK

Python

HTML + CSS

Languages

Spanish Native

English C2

Portuguese B2

German A2

Assistant professor

Central American University (UCA) Managua, Nicaragua

I assisted the economics department of the Central American University in Managua by giving lectures and tutorial sessions for undergraduate courses in Regulation and Antitrust Economics and Social Quantitative Techniques. More specifically, I presented topics related to my experience as an economic analyst at the national antitrust authority (Procompetencia) and as a research analyst at FUNIDES.

Economic Analyst

Jul, 2013 - Jun, 2016

National Institute for the Promotion of Economic Competition(Procompetencia) *Managua, Nicaragua*

As part of the economics department of the national antitrust authority, I supported the senior officers in cases of unfair competition, mergers, and acquisitions. As part of my main responsibilities, I had to clean and analyze firm-level data, prepare tables and plots, delimit relevant markets for mergers and acquisitions cases and write the subsequent economic analysis reports.

Publications

Master thesis:

 Toruño C. (2021). "Political favoritism and social protection policies: Evidence from a cash transfer program in Colombia". Document submitted to Prof. Dr. Krisztina Kis-Katos at the chair of International Economic Policy of the University of Göttingen.

Document available on this link.

Working papers:

- Toruño C. & Granada, D. (2020). "Local democracy in Nicaragua: Study case in the municipalities of El Almendro and Kukrahill" (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.
- Toruño C. & López Espinoza, Á. (2019). "Diagnosis of the demand for technical occupations in times of crisis" (Original document in Spanish). RENET: Managua, Nicaragua

Document available on this link.

- Toruño C. & Huelva, L. & Pacheco, C. (2018). "State of Democracy in Nicaragua 2019" (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.
- Huelva, L. & Pacheco, C. & Toruño C. (2018). "Effects of maternity on the labor supply of women" (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.
- Huelva, L. & Toruño, C. (2017). "Impact of public expenditure in the reduction of poverty and inequality". (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua

Document available on this link.

 Huelva, L. & Pacheco, C. & Toruño C. (2017). "Quality of Education in Nicaragua: Does the children enjoy of the same opportunities?". (Original document in Spanish). FUNIDES: Managua, Nicaragua Document available on this link.

Data Projects

• Colombia 2022: A Twitter Companion

This shiny app contains information about the different presidential candidates related to the 2022 Colombian National Elections based on the daily activity registered over Twitter. The app is divided into three sections: a speech analysis of what the candidates say in their tweets, a social monitoring hub that presents a frequency analysis of what the community expresses about the different candidates and a sentiment trends panel that summarizes the results of a sentiment analysis carried on what the people say about the candidates.

A preliminary version of the app is available here.

• WJP's EU Lawyers Dataset

This shiny app displays the general information on a dataset about lawyers in the European Union. This dataset is mainly built from the web scrapping publicly available information published by national and regional Bar Associations in 27 European Union member countries. The dataset reflects a colossal team effort on web scrapping several different websites, machine translation, geocoding, and data harmonization.

A stable version of the app is available here.

ROLI Map Generator

This streamlit app provides an interactive platform that allows the user to process, draw and download Choropleth Maps using the latest datasets from WJP's Rule of Law Index as data inputs. The app is able to generate world and regional maps while also allowing the user to customize the map.

A preliminary version of the app is available here.